Guide to the Peter E. Palmquist Collection of Male Photographers in the American West
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Research Files, 1888-2003; Series I; 90.5; (332 boxes)
  - California Research Volumes
    - California Photographers
      - California Photographers
        - Volume D: California Photographers Miscellaneous Directory and Census Listings, 1900-1950 (Box 196)
        - Volume E: California Photographers Miscellaneous Directory and Census Listings, 1870-1920 (Box 197)
        - Volume F: California Photographers Miscellaneous Directory and Census Listings, 1850-1920 (Box 198)
        - California Photographers Miscellaneous Directory and Census Listings, 1850-1950 (Box 199)
        - California Photographers Miscellaneous Directory and Listing by City and County, 1869-1925 (Box 200)
        - California Photographers Miscellaneous Listings Arranged by County, 1850-1930 (Box 201)
      - California Photographers: A Bibliographic Reference and Listing of Photographers Active in California Prior to 1900, circa 1975-1982 (Box 202)
      - Mangan, Terry William, and Laverne Mau Dicker. California Photographers, 1852-1920: An Index of Photographers in the Paper Print Collection of the California Historical Society. (San Francisco: California Historical Society), 1977 (Box 203)
      - Some Nineteenth Century California Photographers, compiled by Jean Rosenbloom, 1979 March (Box 204)
      - California Photography, Miscellaneous Articles and Notes (Box 205)
      - Transactions and Reports of the California State Agricultural Society's Fairs, 1856-1881 (Box 206)
      - California Photographers: Miscellaneous Listings, compiled by various persons (Box 207)
        Includes a list of photographers in the San Francisco Bay area to 1900 compiled by James L. Caddick in 1985; a list of daguerreotype photographers in California compiled by John S. Craig in 1989; an undated list of nineteenth century women photographers in California compiled by Peter E. Palmquist; an undated photography shelf list for the California Historical Society; and an undated list of photographers in the John Muir Collection at the University of the Pacific
    - California Photographers Organizations and Photography Schools
      - California Camera Clubs
        - Volume 1: Alameda to San Francisco (Box 208)
        - Volume 2: San Francisco to Women's Federation (Box 209)
        - Volume 3: Alameda to San Diego (Box 210)
        - Volume 4: San Francisco to Miscellaneous (Box 211)
      - Pacific Coast Amateur Photographic Association, Miscellaneous Notes, 1883-1892 (Box 212)
      - California Camera Club, Miscellaneous Notes
        - Volume 1: 1890-1910 (Box 213)
        - Volume 2: 1910-1976 (Box 214)
      - Photographers' Association of California, Miscellaneous Notes, 1903-1924 (Box 215)
      - Los Angeles Camera Club, Miscellaneous Notes, 1900-1941 (Box 216)
      - The Photographers' Association of America, Entries for California in Classified Membership Directories, 1940-1958 (Box 217)
      - California Photography Schools and Periodicals, Miscellaneous Notes (Box 218)
    - California Stereographs
      - Yosemite and California, Stereo Matches and Notes (Box 219)
      - Inventory of Stereo Views at Yosemite National Park (Box 220)
      - Notes on Yosemite, compiled by Peter E. Palmquist and Jim Crain, circa 1996 (Box 221)
    - Photography in San Francisco
      - The Daguerreotype in San Francisco 1849-1860 (Box 222)
      - Index of Photography in San Francisco, 1850-1900, compiled by Anthony R. White, circa 1980 (Box 223)
      - Reports of the Mechanics' Institute Exhibitions in San Francisco, 1858-1896, and, The Mechanics' Fair Daily Press, 1864-1871 (Box 224)
      - San Francisco Photographic Artists' Association, Miscellaneous Notes, 1866 (Box 225)
      - The San Francisco Photographic Salons of 1901, 1902, and 1903 (Box 226)
    - Photography and Art in California
      - Notes on Some Artists of the California Gold Rush Period (Box 227)
      - California Engravings from Gleason's Pictorial Drawing Room Companion (1851-1859), Illustrated California News (1850), The California Pictorial for 1860, and The Wide West (1854-1857) (Box 228)
    - Photography and Art in the Yosemite Valley
      - A Yosemite Chronology: Artists, Photographers, and Other Key Figures and Events, compiled by Louis H. Smaus, circa 1986 (Box 229)
      - Stereographs of Yosemite and Big Trees Published by E. and H. T. Anthony and Company, compiled by Louis H. Smaus, circa 1986 (Box 230)
        Documents stereographic photographs created by Thomas C. Roches and Charles Leander Weed
    - Photographic Collections in California
      - Photo Collection, The Oakland Museum, 1992 June 10 (Box 231)
      - Union Guide to California Cased Images, compiled by Drew Heath Johnson and Peter E. Palmquist, 1996; 2 volumes (Box 232)
    - California History
      - Sierra Nevada House Register, 1855-1859, 2 volumes and 1 box
        Photocopy of the register for the Sierra Nevada House, a hotel in Coloma, California, from the original in the collection of Vivenne Bekeart, San Francisco, California
        Two duplicate volumes and one unbound photocopy.
        - Sierra Nevada House Register, 1855-1859, photocopy (Box 233)
        - Sierra Nevada House Register, 1855-1859, photocopy (Box 234)
        - Sierra Nevada House Register, 1855-1859, unbound photocopy (Box 235)
      - Carrillo, Alma McDaniel, and Eleanora Carrillo de Haney. The Carrillo Family in Sonoma County; History and Memories, 1974 (Box 236)
    - Writings of Richard Steven Street
      Biographical/Historical note
      Richard Steven Street (born 1946) is a photographer, historian and journalist specializing in California agriculture.
      - Writings of Richard Steven Street (Box 237)
      - Street, Richard Steven. California Farmworkers: A Photographic History, 1850-2000, unpublished manuscript, circa 1998 (Box 238)
  - Geographical Research Volumes
    This subseries is arranged under headings for geographical regions, including World Photographers and the countries of Bolivia, Canada, and the United States of America, followed by regions in the United States of America consisting of the Great Lakes Region and Trans-Mississippi West, and then by individual states arranged alphabetically.
    This subseries chiefly consists of geographical studies of photography and directories of photographers in regions throughout the United States collected by Palmquist, which he then bound into volumes.
    Much of the material gathered by Palmquist supported his multi-volume dictionary of photographers working in the United States between 1840 and 1860, which he co-authored with Thomas R. Kailbourn: Pioneer Photographers of the Far West: A Biographical Dictionary, 1840-1865 (2000), and Pioneer Photographers from the Mississippi to the Continental Divide: A Biographical Dictionary (2005).
    Many volumes include material compiled by historical archaeologist Alan Roland Woolworth during his work as a research fellow at the Minnesota Historical Society.
    - World Photographers
      - Walters, Judith Allison. Photographers of North America, Great Britain and Europe: A Computerized Listing of Not All, but Approximately 1800 Different Photographers with Cities and Some Dates of Operation, Covering the Years 1840-1939. (Bothell, Washington: J. A. Walters), 1980 (Box 239)
      - Directories of Photographers: An Annotated World Bibliography, compiled by Richard Rudisill and Steven F. Joseph, 1998 (Box 240)
    - Bolivia
      - Pioneer Photography in Bolivia: Directory of Daguerrotypists and Photographers, 1840s-1930s, compiled by Daniel Buck, 2000 January (Box 241)
    - Canada
      - Nineteenth Century Photographers on the Canadian Prairies, compiled by Hugh A. Dempsy, 1978 (Box 242)
    - United States of America
      - Sprange, Walter. The "Blue Book" of Amateur Photographers, (Sprange's Annual): Being a Directory of the Various Amateur Photographic Societies in the United States of America, and Containing a Complete List of the Officers and Members of the Societies, with Their Addresses. (Beach Bluff, Massachusetts: W. Sprange), 1893 (Box 243)
      - Sprange, Walter. The "Blue Book" of Amateur Photographers, (Sprange's Annual): Being a Directory of the Various Amateur Photographic Societies in the United States of America, and Containing a Complete List of the Officers and Members of the Societies, with Their Addresses. (Beach Bluff, Massachusetts: W. Sprange), 1895 (Box 244)
      - Simons, Maurice M. "Apollo's Agents on Earth: A Selective Bio-Bibliography of Nineteenth Century American Photographers", 1978 May (Box 245)
        Thesis (Master of Arts), University of California, Los Angeles
      - Daguerreotypists in the United States, 1839-1860, compiled by John Craig, 1987 September 8 (Box 246)
      - Goodyear, Frank Henry. "Constructing a National Landscape: Photography and Tourism in Nineteenth-Century America", 1998 (Box 247)
        Thesis (Ph. D.), University of Texas at Austin
      - Miscellaneous Checklists and Collection Notes, United States of America (Organized by States), compiled by Peter E. Palmquist (Box 248)
      - Photographers Miscellaneous Listings Arranged by State and County, by various compilers (Box 249)
    - Great Lakes Region
      - Data on Photographers at Duluth, Superior, Wisconsin, the North Shore of Lake Superior, and the Minnesota Iron Ranges, compiled by Alan Roland Woolworth, 1988-1995 (Box 250)
    - Trans-Mississippi West
      - Pioneer Photographers of the Far West, compiled by Peter E. Palmquist and Thomas R. Kailbourn
        - Volume 1: Anonymous (Box 251)
        - Volume 2: ABC to Ayres (Box 252)
        - Volume 3: Babbitt to Beals (Box 253)
        - Volume 4: Beals to Bradley (Box 254)
        - Volume 5: Branham to Britt (Box 255)
        - Volume 6: Britton to Burnham (Box 256)
        - Volume 7: Burr to Cannon (Box 257)
        - Volume 8: Carden to Celarie (Box 258)
        - Volume 9: Cextrom to Claveau (Box 259)
        - Volume 10: Clayton to Crane (Box 260)
        - Volume 11: Craven to Dennen (Box 261)
        - Volume 12: Denny to Dyer (Box 262)
        - Volume 13: Eagle to Faul (Box 263)
        - Volume 14: Feilner to Flugge (Box 264)
        - Volume 15: Foley to Garge (Box 265)
        - Volume 16: Galvez to Halsey (Box 266)
        - Volume 17: Hamer to Hearing (Box 267)
        - Volume 18: Heilge to Hodapp (Box 268)
        - Volume 19: Hodkins to Hutton (Box 269)
        - Volume 20: Ibarra to Johnson (Box 270)
        - Volume 21: Johnson to Junk (Box 271)
        - Volume 22: Kaltschimdt to Koch (Box 272)
        - Volume 23: Kochenrath to Leonard (Box 273)
        - Volume 24: LePlongeon to Loreozen (Box 274)
        - Volume 25: Louis to Maynard (Box 275)
        - Volume 26: Mazzucchelli to Miller (Box 276)
        - Volume 27: Mills to Nichols (Box 277)
        - Volume 28: Niswander to Pierce (Box 278)
        - Volume 29: Peligrini to Plecker (Box 279)
        - Volume 30: Plumbe to Robinson (Box 280)
        - Volume 30: Robles to Ryder (Box 281)
          Duplication of "Volume 30" represents the numbering of the volume
        - Volume 31: Sabine to Scripture (Box 282)
        - Volume 32: Searles to Sherriff (Box 283)
        - Volume 33: Shew to Smith (Box 284)
        - Volume 34: Smith to Spooner (Box 285)
        - Volume 35: Sprague to Stratton (Box 286)
        - Volume 36: Stuart to Taber (Box 287)
        - Volume 37: Taber to Titus (Box 288)
        - Volume 38: Todd to Vallejo (Box 289)
        - Volume 39: Van Allen to Wadsworth (Box 290)
        - Volume 40: Wakefield to Watkins (Box 291)
        - Volume 41: Watkins to Winter (Box 292)
        - Volume 42: Winter to Zuber (Box 293)
      - Western Artists and Photographers, Miscellaneous Writings (Box 294)
      - Western Artists and Photographers, Miscellaneous Writings (Box 295)
      - Photography of Indians, Miscellaneous Accounts, 3 volumes (Box 296)
      - Photography of Indians, Miscellaneous Accounts (Box 297)
      - Photography of Indians, Miscellaneous Accounts (Box 298)
      - Minnesota, Dakota, and Montana Gazetteer and Business Directory, 1878-1992, by R. L. Polk and Company, St. Paul, Minnesota, compiled by Alan Roland Woolworth, 1988-1995 (Box 299)
      - Western Landscape Photography Various Accounts (Box 300)
      - Westward Travel Accounts, Gold Rush Narratives, Etc. (Box 301)
      - Western Panoramas, Cosmoramas, Etc.: Collected Notes 1840-1865, compiled by Peter E. Palmquist and Thomas R. Kailbourn
        - Volume 1: Anon to Morell, 1997 (Box 302)
        - Volume 2: Morrison to Wormer, Miscellaneous, 1997 (Box 303)
    - Alabama
      - Robb, Frances Osborn. Alabama Photography 1839-1941: An Illustrated History, typescript, 1995 May (Box 304)
        Includes a checklist of Alabama women photographers, 1839-1941
    - Arizona
      - Lane, Anne Marie. "A Preliminary Catalogue of Nineteenth-Century Books Illustrated with Original Photographs at the Center for Creative Photography, University of Arizona, Tuscon", 1991 April (Box 305)
        Undergraduate Paper for a History of Photography course taught by Keith McElroy at the University of Arizona
    - Hawaii
      - Davis, Lynn Ann, From California Gold Fields: Daguerreotypists in Hawaii, 1985 (Box 306)
    - Massachusetts
      - Photographic Collections in the Boston Public Library, Miscellaneous Listings, compiled by Peter E. Palmquist (Box 307)
      - Daguerreian Advertisements, Boston, 1839-1854, compiled by Peter E. Palmquist (Box 308)
    - Minnesota
      - Census and Other Statistical Data on Photography in Minnesota, 1850, compiled by Alan Roland Woolworth, 1988-1995 (Box 309)
      - Minnesota Daguerreians and Ambrotypers 1848-70, compiled by Alan Roland Woolworth, 1988-1995 (Box 310)
      - Photographers in St. Paul, Minnesota, circa 1850-1930, compiled by Alan Roland Woolworth, 1988-1995 (Box 311)
      - Photographers in St. Anthony and Minneapolis, Minnesota, circa 1850-1930, compiled by Alan Roland Woolworth, 1988-1995 (Box 312)
      - Entries on Winona Photographers from City Directories, 1866-1930, compiled by Alan Roland Woolworth, 1988-1995 (Box 313)
      - Photographers Listed in Saint Paul, Minnesota Directories, 1875-1880, compiled by Alan Roland Woolworth, 1988-1995 (Box 314)
      - Minnesotan's Views on Photographs and Uses of Them in Homes, Albums, Etc., compiled by Alan Roland Woolworth, 1988-1995 (Box 315)
      - Notes and Papers of G. Hubert Smith on Minnesota Photographers and Photography, compiled by Alan Roland Woolworth, 1988-1995 (Box 316)
      - Photographers at Stillwater, Washington County, Minnesota, compiled by Alan Roland Woolworth, 1988-1995 (Box 317)
      - Minnesota Photographers: A List of Practitioners Compiled from City Directories, by Patricia Harpole, 1988-1995 (Box 318)
      - Early Illustrations of the Minnesota Region from Harper's Weekly Magazine, compiled by Alan R. Woolworth, 1988-1995 (Box 319)
      - Painted Panoramas Relating to Minnesota, Miscellaneous Notes, compiled by Alan R. Woolworth, 1988-1995 (Box 320)
    - Nebraska
      - Nebraska Photographers, compiled by John E. Carter, 1993 (Box 321)
    - Ohio
      - Ohio Photographers to 1900, compiled by John Waldsmith, circa 1979 (Box 322)
    - Pennsylvania
      - Guide to the Photographers of Chester County, Pennsylvania, compiled by the Chester Historical Society, circa 1985 (Box 323)
      - Weprich, Thomas M. "The Early Photographic History of Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, 1839-1904", 1991 December (Box 324)
        Thesis (Master of Arts), Pennsylvania State University
    - Texas
      - Texas Photographers' Biographies, compiled by David Haynes, 1989 (Box 325)
    - Washington, District of Columbia
      - Baty, Laurie Anne. "Photographers of Washington, D.C., 1870-1885", 1979 (Box 326)
        Thesis (Master of Arts), George Washington University
    - Wisconsin
      - Pioneer Wisconsin Photographers, compiled by John Adams Graf (Box 327)
      - Survey of Daguerreotypes in the Collection of the Neville Public Museum, Green Bay, Wisconsin, compiled by John F. Graf, 1993 July 30 (Box 328)
  - Asian American Photographers Research
    This subseries chiefly consists of consists of biographical files and miscellaneous notes about Asian American photographers working principally in California. Palmquist collected much of the material to support his participation in the exhibition "With New Eyes: Toward an Asian American Art History of the West" at the Fine Arts Gallery of San Francisco State University, September 24, 1995, to October 26, 1995.
    - Biographical Files
      - Ahashi, Kaoru, to Kuroko, F. H. (Box 329)
      - Maimuro, T., to Zshiguiro, N. (Box 330)
    - Research Binders
      - Chinese American Photographers (Box 331)
      - Japanese American Photographers (Box 332)
- Photographic Materials, circa 1840-2003; Series II; (231 boxes)
  Series II is organized into six subseries: Photographic Materials, Oversize Photographic Materials, Photograph Albums, Panoramic Photographs, and Framed Photographs.
  This series consists of photographic materials collected by Palmquist that were created by or document individual male photographers chiefly in the American West. It consists of vintage photographic prints created by photographers, as well as many copy photographs created by Palmquist of vintage photographic prints. The series documents the breadth of work by male photographers from the middle of the nineteenth century to the late twentieth century. Works by a photographer may appear in multiple subseries.
  For most of the listed photographers, the collection has only a few photographs. Individual photographers with significant quantities of material in the collection include Frank C. Aston, Walter T. Fitch, Louis Herman Heller, Thomas Houseworth, Benjamin Franklin Howland, Charles Wallace Jacob Johnson, George Daniels Morse, John Pitcher Spooner, Isaiah West Taber, Robert H. Vance, Carleton E. Watkins, and Chester L. Weed. Firms with substantial groups of material in the collection include Bradley & Rulofson, Bushnell Photo Company, and The Imperial Studio.
  Specific dates of materials or image creation dates were not captured during processing.
  Nearly all of the individuals and firms with photographic materials in this series have biographical files in Series I.
  Photographic materials related to women photographers active in the American West are included in the Peter Palmquist Collection of Women in Photography (WA MSS S-2600).
  Photographic materials related to male photographers active in Humboldt County, California, are included in the Peter Palmquist Collection of Humboldt County, California, Male Photographers (WA MSS S-2670).
  Cased photographs related to male photographers active in the American West are included in the Peter Palmquist Cased Photographs Collection (WA Photos 402). Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University.
  - Photographic Materials
    This subseries is arranged alphabetically by the surname of the photographer or the corporate name of the studio.
    This subseries consists of vintage photographic prints, copy photographs created by Palmquist, photographic negatives, associated publications, and ephemera created by male photographers and photography studios operated by men.
    Photographic materials with dimensions larger than 22 x 29 centimeters (8.7 x 11.4 inches), are located in the Oversize Photographic Materials subseries.
    Each entry in the subseries represents a single folder with at least one photographic print. Entries with more than one folder are noted.
    - A Kolor (Box 333)
    - A. C. Company (Box 333)
    - Abbott, Charles (Box 333)
    - Abell & Priest, 6 (Box 334)
    - Abell & Son (Box 334)
    - Abell & Welsh (Box 334)
    - Abell, Frank George, Jr., 4 (Box 334)
    - Abell's Art-Studio Car. (Box 334)
    - ACME Photo Service (Box 333)
    - Adams, Ansel, 8 (Box 335)
    - Adams, Charles Albert, 3 (Box 333)
    - Adams, J. M. (Box 333)
    - Adams, Rodney F. (Box 333)
    - Addos & Koch (Box 333)
    - Addis, Alfred Shea (Box 333)
    - Addis, Robert (Box 333)
    - Adelsbach, P. F. (Box 333)
    - Agner, Charles A. (Box 333)
    - Aichberg, Christian (Box 333)
    - Alaska Photo Company (Box 333)
    - Albertype Company (Box 333)
    - Albrecht, Herman Oliver (Box 333)
    - Aldine Studio, 2 (Box 333)
    - Alisky, Charles (Box 333)
    - Allaire, M. and C. Bowden (Box 333)
    - Alt, Rudolph (Box 333)
    - Alter, C. F. (Box 333)
    - Altpeter & Anderson (Box 333)
    - Altpeter, Louis (Box 333)
    - Alvord, E. D. (Box 333)
    - Alworth and Piece (Box 333)
    - Ambrose, Goodhue (Box 333)
    - American and Australasian Photographic Company (Box 333)
    - American Art Studio (Box 333)
    - American Industrial Photo Company (Box 333)
    - American Society of Camera Collectors (Box 333)
    - American Stereoscopic Company (Box 333)
    - American View Company (Box 333)
    - Amic Gazan de la Perriere, T. (Box 333)
    - Amsden, W. O. (Box 333)
    - Anaya, Carlos (Box 333)
    - Anderson Photo Service (Box 333)
    - Anderson, Hugh, 3 (Box 336)
    - Anderson, Macfarlane (Box 337)
    - Andrews, Thomas P. (Box 337)
    - Angelus Studio (Box 337)
    - Anthony, Edward & Henry T. (Box 337)
    - Antrim, Benajah Jay (Box 337)
    - Appleton, D. E. & Company (Box 337)
    - Archer, Fred, 8 (Box 338)
    - Armstrong, Thomas (Box 337)
    - Arnold, Richard J., 5 (Box 339)
    - Arnold, William T. (Box 337)
    - Arriola (Box 337)
    - Arriola & Edell (Box 337)
    - Arrowsmith, W. H. (Box 337)
    - Art Palace (Box 337)
    - Artcraft Camera Shop (Box 337)
    - Asbeck, August, 2 (Box 337)
    - Asher, Julius, 9 (Box 340)
    - Associated Photographers of the Sacramento and San Joaquin Valleys (Box 337)
    - Aston, Frank C., 16 (Box 341)
    - Atkinson (Box 337)
    - Atlas View Company (Box 337)
    - Atwood, B. L. (Box 337)
    - Auburn Post Card Company (Box 337)
    - Austin & Company (Box 337)
    - Austin Studios, 3 (Box 342)
    - Avery, James W. (Box 337)
    - Aydelotte, C. L. (Box 337)
    - Ayers, Thomas Almond (Box 337)
    - Babbitt, E. L. (Box 343)
    - Babcock, Charles F., 3 (Box 343)
    - Baccilieri, Peter A. (Box 343)
    - Bacon & Korne (Box 343)
    - Bacon, De Groat, & Kellogg (Box 343)
    - Bacon, H. M. (Box 343)
    - Bacon, J. Edmund (Box 343)
    - Bacon, Shirley V. (Box 343)
    - Bacon, William O. (Box 343)
    - Bailey & Burnett (Box 343)
    - Bailey & Cramer (Box 343)
    - Bailey, Abram P. (Box 343)
    - Bainbridge, C. E. (Box 343)
    - Baker & Johnston (Box 344)
    - Baker, Charles Leverett (Box 344)
    - Baker, E. W. (Box 344)
    - Baker, Edward W. (Box 344)
    - Baker, Isaac Wallace (Box 344)
    - Baker, John W. (Box 344)
    - Baker, R. J. (Box 344)
    - Baker, S. F. (Box 344)
    - Baker, Walter T. (Box 344)
    - Baldwin (Box 345)
    - Baldwin & Betancue (Box 345)
    - Baldwin & Blondal (Box 345)
    - Baldwin & Clement (Box 345)
    - Baldwin & Kerlin (Box 345)
    - Baldwin Studio (Box 345)
    - Baldwin, John E. D., 4 (Box 345)
    - Ball, George (Box 345)
    - Bamboca, E. (Box 345)
    - Banbrock, W. E. (Box 345)
    - Bardell Pictures (Box 345)
    - Bardwell, Jex J. (Box 345)
    - Barnett, Edwin Z. (Box 345)
    - Barrows, 2 (Box 345)
    - Bartel, C. (Box 346)
    - Bartlett, Adelbert (Box 346)
    - Bartley, F. H. (Box 346)
    - Bass, Thomas (Box 346)
    - Bast, W., 2 (Box 346)
    - Batchelder & Company (Box 346)
    - Batchelder, Benjamin Pierce, 4 (Box 347)
    - Batchelder, P. M. & Company (Box 346)
    - Bauer (Box 346)
    - Bayley & Cramer (Box 346)
    - Bayley & Johnston (Box 346)
    - Bayley & O'Hara (Box 346)
    - Bayley & Winter (Box 346)
    - Bayley, Charles H. (Box 346)